<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Otto DIY</title>
    <description>interactive robot that anyone can make! #OttoDIY "build your own opensource robot" 3D printable and powered by #Arduino. ottobot, ottorobot, maker faire, 3D print robot, STEAM education.</description>
    <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Otto builders around the world!</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:17:05 -0800</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/map</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/map</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Otto builders are the community of Otto DIY&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is an open map that we created of builds of various #OttoDIY Projects and some of initiatives, companies, maker spaces or learning centers that have made or use Otto in their workshops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How many &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/hashtag/ottobuilders?source=feed_text&amp;epa=HASHTAG"&gt;#Ottobuilders&lt;/a&gt; are actually around the globe? and How many &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/hashtag/ottodiy?source=feed_text&amp;epa=HASHTAG"&gt;#OttoDIY&lt;/a&gt; has been built? We are about to figure out but we need your help to help us collect all Otto robots and related makers in this map.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. &lt;/strong&gt;Click on the&lt;strong&gt; add marker&lt;/strong&gt; button on the top left (below the search bar) you can click in any place of the world or drop it approximately in your city or just search your address on the top bar to be more precise and then just click in &lt;strong&gt;"add to map"&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; You can input your name (companies also possible to have visibility), choose the color same as your Otto!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.&lt;/strong&gt; Put a short (relevant) description of you Robot build, which project you have done (DIY, PLUS, ARMS or planing other?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.&lt;/strong&gt; Upload a picture and/or video (it´s also possible to add a YouTube link).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.&lt;/strong&gt; Email or Website, if you wanna be contacted by other builders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By this you JOIN OUR INTERNATIONAL NETWORK OF ROBOT MAKERS! for future events, partnership and collaboration. Please help us also to hunt places of robot interest!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="font-size: 160%; text-align: center;"&gt;Are you ready for world domination?🤖👾&lt;/p&gt;&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/map&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teach your Kids to code</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 01:58:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/teach</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/teach</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Coding is the lingua franca for all citizen in a modern technological society. By adapting any programming language your kids can learn very important skills, such as abstraction of a problem, defining and structuring a solution and to use a sequence of simple steps to fulfill complex tasks. Beside all the educational benefits of learning to use a programming language it is a lot of fun to see and experience your own programs while performing their autonomous tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another important skill within the actual technological society is to understand and control robotic hardware or electronics in general.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nothing is more exiting for your kids as if something moves, makes a sound or blinks a lot of lights. Believe me when I say that kids are native robot and automation enthusiasts!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That said, I was really exited as I read about a vivid community of electronics and programming experts that shared the same idea of building the open educational robotics platform &lt;a href="http://ottodiy.com/"&gt;OttoDIY&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OttoDIY offers all necessary resources, such as electronics, servos, sensors along with 3D printing models of the robot’s body parts to quickly jump into the world of electronics and robotic motion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The OttoDIY community does share all information that is necessary to quickly print your own Otto robot and assemble the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the company I work for (kudos to &lt;a href="https://www.dynatrace.com/"&gt;Dynatrace&lt;/a&gt;) strongly supports innovation and coding for kids. Therefore, I had the chance to print our own Otto robot within the Dynatrace lab and I was astonished how easy it is to reproduce the body parts offered on &lt;a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/groups/ottodiy/"&gt;thingiverse&lt;/a&gt;. See some impressions of the printing process below:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Otto’s brain arrived some weeks later and we immediately started to assemble the complete OttoDIY robot. With the assembly instructions given by &lt;a...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/teach&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>bipedal robots</title>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 22:00:19 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/bipeds</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/bipeds</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Otto it is a robot with legs proposed as an approach to bipedal robots. Otto, still having a very simple mechanical configuration, has the ability to perform many movements such as walking, show emotions or dance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Normally, all texts dedicated to bipedal robots begin by praising the advantages that robots with legs can have with respect to robots moved by wheels or other rotating elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, I would like to approach the subject from another point of view: the robots with legs are cool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They are awesome! without giving it more laps, and how cool it is worth breaking your head with impossible mechanical configurations, horrible equations and frustrating results. They are not very grateful robots, their start-up is usually slow (and desolating), and it is rare that they work at the first attempt "&lt;u&gt;like all robots"&lt;/u&gt;. In general, these robots are a challenge for both engineers and fans of robotics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Focusing on robots with two legs, that is bipeds; we can find countless concepts: from single bipeds with a single engine to humanoids with more than twenty joints.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A good biped robot must be able to modify the position of its mechanical elements, to dynamically move its center of gravity. In fact, this ability will be the most important ingredient when it comes to getting our robot to stand up. A robot in a static position will remain stable if the projection of its center of gravity on the horizontal surface is within the area bounded by the support points of the robot. In summary, for a robot to walk, it is necessary to be able to support its weight on one foot or another, at different moments of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When designing and building bipedal robots, a first option is robots with 2-3 degrees of freedom. If there is a father of this type of robot, that is David Buckley. In 1998 he built the BigFoot, a robot that with only two servos has the ability to move forward, backward and make turns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/bipeds&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>how to calibrate your own robot?</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 22:51:40 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/calibration</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/calibration</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post we will cover the whole topic that is driving a lot of uncertain among builders if they are actually assembling in the right way their robots but first what is calibration? As Wikipedia says:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"&lt;b&gt;Calibration &lt;/b&gt;is the comparison of measurement values delivered by a device under test with those of a calibration standard of known accuracy. Such a standard could be another measurement device of known accuracy, a device generating the quantity to be measured such as a voltage, sound tone, or a physical artefact"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In our case will be "the calibration of the 4 servo motors"&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you understand the definition you will find out that you do NOT need to calibrate your Otto to be able to work properly because the calibration is ONLY for precise movements like let's say "straight walk" or standing in one leg without falling.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Why my Otto legs and feet are twisted?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is a very frequent question in our &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/ottodiy/"&gt;Otto builder community&lt;/a&gt; and emails, Many Otto builders think they need to calibrate their robot because after assembly they faced this problem, but the true is that, they might skip the important warning in the instruction manual while putting the motors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Otto uses 180 degrees servo motors that means the rotation is intentionally limited (we don't want the legs of Otto spinning like freewheels), if you see above picture, the first step is to make sure the servo motor is properly in the middle of the 180 degrees rotation (90 degrees) you don't have to and you won't be that precise at this point (a tolerance of 5 degrees is fine) but is &lt;strong&gt;absolutely necessary&lt;/strong&gt; to put the white servo key in the center otherwise the foot in this case won't turn from side to side.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same principle applies to the legs and to Otto PLUS metal gear motors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give a try! and now probably you discover that...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/calibration&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 easy ways to design your own robot</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 22:33:10 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/design</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/design</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;sometimes you just want your Otto to stand out among all other robots made by the community, that is when creativity and imagine come to play and is very easy when we have broad tools to helps us to create a whole new world of characters and stories to create STEAM activities that promote the "Art and Design" as innovative skills to train the lateral thinking; now we will introduce our 4 favorite ways of customize your own robot:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="s-text-color-custom2"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. customizer APP by Thingiverse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;do you want to make your &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/hashtag/ottodiy?source=feed_text"&gt;#OttoDIY&lt;/a&gt; bigger or smaller more fat or skinnier, adapt to a different board or just simply have fun designing and customizing your own Otto? well is very easy! get a Thingiverse account, open the customizer APP and start to create your own remixes! &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/hashtag/thingalert?source=feed_text"&gt;#thingalert&lt;/a&gt; https://www.thingiverse.com/apps/customizer/run?thing_id=1568652&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;the APP is very intuitive just need to tune the parameters as you need to "create your thing" that will generate automatically all STL files ready for 3d print&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"you just modify the parameters on the left and preview the result of the 3d print partes on the right"&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="s-text-color-custom2"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. paper-craft skins and stickers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;as mentioned&lt;a target="_blank" href="http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/infinitywar"&gt; in the previous post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;you can easily create new characters based on the shape of ? Otto we find already many tools online that help you to just download cut and print these character and to make it more easy we created a white FREE template for #Ottobuilders who wants to draw, color, paint on top of the cube-craft and dress on Otto. And we already created some common cool characters and will continue adding more by request, so if you need...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/design&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>suit up your Otto for avengers infinity war</title>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 23:18:49 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/infinitywar</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/infinitywar</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Suiting up &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ottodiy?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ottodiy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/DIYrobot?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;DIYrobot&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the release of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AvengersInfinityWar?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;AvengersInfinityWar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; movie like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/IronMan?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;IronMan&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; any other character from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Marvel?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;Marvel&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that you will like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/papercrafts?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;papercrafts&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ottobuilder?src=hash"&gt;&lt;s&gt;#&lt;/s&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ottobuilder&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We adjusted the previous stickers designs that were a little complicated to find the right paper , then print, then cut precisely and then stick on the robot parts was a good result at the beginning but with time the labels just fall off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So to make it easier for all Otto builders we just redesign for paper craft with inspiration from http://cubeecraft.com to just resize, print, fold and suit Ottos with multiple creative characters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started adjusting our current graphics paper craft art by &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/Gus-Santome-Mini-Papercraft-340166079371197/"&gt;Gus Santome Mini Papercraft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/avengers/"&gt;Avengers&lt;/a&gt; but the possibilities and number of characters are endless thanks to websites like cubecraft or cubefold-craft.com which let you download the designs fro FREE to use as long as you don't make a businesses out of it, so exactly like them an making honor to our super truly open source hardware we also share them for FREE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just print in A4 size sheet on label paper then cut them following the silhouette of the shapes. Looking forward to see your Avenger Infinity war Otto share some pics of your creations in our social media, together with the Otto builder comunity we should make all...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/infinitywar&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Make magazine article about Otto</title>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 23:43:47 -0800</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/magazine</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/magazine</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Head into 2018 with a great new issue of Make:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cover story is a wonderful profile about Shenzhen, China-based maker Naomi Wu and accompanied by profiles of other inspiring makers from that region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p style="font-size: 160%; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="s-text-color-red"&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Make Vol. 61: Spotlight Shenzhen&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="font-size: 160%; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="s-text-color-red"&gt;&lt;sub&gt;check the page 64 "DIY Bipedal Robot "&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open source, educational, programmable and customizable, Otto can dance and avoid obstacles initially as quick start but you can easily expand and make more advance robots with Bluetooth, touch sensors and 3D printing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/magazine&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Otto builder spotlight "Davor"</title>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 22:21:22 -0800</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/davor</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/davor</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Otto builders are doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Otto builders are incredible! just by looking in YouTube, Facebook and Twitter we gathered our first series of remarkable developments that are contributing to Otto DIY open robot project in certain way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Otto builders are incredible! just by looking in YouTube, Facebook and Twitter we gathered our first series of remarkable developments that are contributing to Otto DIY open robot project in certain way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We are having a series of" spotlight blog post" about outstanding Otto builders and their openness to the community. Today we have Davor Levstek​ from Europe here is what he said:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I live in Croatia and work as quality control inspector, testing railway vehicles. My hobbies are electronics, 3D printing and RC toys. This is my first #OttoDIY&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My interests in Arduino and 3d printing started with Otto. When I made my first Otto I wanted to make it better, but 3d printing here was too expensive or quality wasn’t satisfying so I decided to make my own 3D printer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, I started modifying Otto so I added Bluetooth and modified code so I can use it with Zowi app. In next version I added RGB led for nose, and thanks to Ayunken from youtube I managed to add LED matrix for mouth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also played with LiPo battery and charger, I have one Otto with it, but I’m still not satisfied with how it works so I’m still trying to find best way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the meantime I made Otto XL which is 6mm larger than original so I can use 4*AA batteries with led matrix display. That is the last Otto I made and it has following options: custom PCB, BT, RGB led nose,LED matrix, AA batteries, sound sensor and touch sensor for changing modes. Otto Minion XL:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also printed one xpider so my Ottos have some company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: center;" class="s-text-color-custom2"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/fy4phGppZ8f0s8Yn1"&gt;Here are more...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/davor&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Otto builder spotlight "Jason"</title>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 18:25:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/jason</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/jason</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Otto builders are doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Otto builders are incredible! just by looking in YouTube, Facebook and Twitter we gathered our first series of remarkable developments that are contributing to Otto DIY open robot project in certain way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Otto builders are incredible! just by looking in YouTube, Facebook and Twitter we gathered our first series of remarkable developments that are contributing to Otto DIY open robot project in certain way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is the start of a series of "spotlight blog post" about outstanding Otto builders and their openness to the community Starting from Jason Snow from UK! here is what he said:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"&lt;a target="_blank" href="http://ottodiy.us14.list-manage.com/track/click?u=77b4a685cda83b940c8395bf8&amp;id=d1e021f0d0&amp;e=25c92201c6"&gt;I made a basic Otto from Thingiverse&lt;/a&gt; and then noticed the Otto plus calling for the community to help develop and evolve Otto further, I bought a &lt;strong&gt;max 7219 led matrix &lt;/strong&gt;and set about adding it and debugging your 'to do' code to work with it"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to leave out &lt;strong&gt;Tito&lt;/strong&gt;. I gave him the same functionality as &lt;strong&gt;Otto DIY+(PLUS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before Otto I made a &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://ottodiy.us14.list-manage.com/track/click?u=77b4a685cda83b940c8395bf8&amp;id=dd4b4e624e&amp;e=25c92201c6"&gt;Scout. &lt;/a&gt; So with this in mind and the fact I had previously printed wheels and had rubber orings I decided to give Otto plus some wheels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jason says: "I added Bluetooth and with the Zowi app set about tweaking the code further"&lt;/p&gt;Next was to modify the original STL files to allow the additional room in the body and head to allow the led matrix to fit.&lt;p&gt;Also testing &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://ottodiy.us14.list-manage.com/track/click?u=77b4a685cda83b940c8395bf8&amp;id=e696e513ff&amp;e=25c92201c6"&gt;#starwars&lt;/a&gt; sounds for Otto :D&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;photos published by Jason Snow in Thingiverse, sharing his work back to the...&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/jason&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>the journey of Otto  </title>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2017 22:12:19 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/journey</link>
      <guid>http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/journey</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3&gt; where Otto come from? &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p class="s-text-color-black"&gt;the journey of Otto, presented in the 2017 Xi'an China Maker Faire, is the adventure of how 2 Latin makers with a lot of passion for robots are enabling everyone in the world to build their own robots.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="s-text-color-black"&gt;we will have a video of the speech; meanwhile have a look to the presentation the slides:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;concept picture of the robots we have created throughout this 3 years adventure&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;p class="s-text-color-custom2" style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See the full presentation here: &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.slideshare.net/CamiloParraPalacio/the-journey-of-otto"&gt;the journey of Otto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;a href=http://www.ottodiy.com/blog/journey&gt;Read More&lt;/a&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
